A Guide to the O. A. Hawkins Collection of Virginiana, 1770-1877
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
O. A. Hawkins Collection of Virginiana, 1770-1877
Library of Virginia
14038
.225 cubic feet
O. A. Hawkins
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from the Anderson Galleries, New York, New York, 2 May 1921.
Biographical Information
Olive A. Hawkins was born in Richmond, Virginia, 10 December 1855. Educated in local schools, he graduated with a degree from the Medical College of Virginia and became a pharmacist. Hawkins then became a salesman for a clothing company before joining the grocery firm of Wirt E. Taylor. In 1890, he became commissioner of revenue for Richmond and served in that capacity for twelve years. Hawkins then became part of a real estate firm called Buford and Hawkins. He then worked for the Richmond Trust Company as head of its real estate division. Hawkins also worked for Craig, Miller, and Company, an insurance and real estate firm. He and his wife Ida Wilson Hawkins (1856-1937) had two children. Hawkins died in Richmond 11 September 1934, and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content Information
Collection, 1770-1877, of Virginiana collected by Olive A. Hawkins consisting of correspondence, inventories, accounts, instructions, invoices, receipts, bills of exchanges, powers of attorney, certificates of sale and transfer, obituaries, portrait, mortgages, treasury notes, membership certificates. Collection is divided into two series: Series I: Norborne Berkeley, Baron de Botetourt estate papers, 1770-1772; and Series II: Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1787-1877.
Series I: Norborne Berkeley, Baron de Botetourt estate papers, 1770-1772, contains correspondence between Robert Carter Nicholas, William Nelson, John Randolph, George Wythe, and John Blair on one hand and the Duke of Beaufort on the other regarding the death of Botetourt who was serving as the governor of Virginia; the disposition of his estate in Virginia; his burial; and a monument for Botetourt. Papers include inventory of his library, possessions, and furniture in the Governor's Palace in Williamsburg, Virginia; accounts of William Marshman and Thomas Fuller, managers of Botetourt's estate; receipts; invoices; bill of exchange from Richard Hanson to Lyonel and Samuel Lyde for Robert Carter Nicholas which Nicholas signed over to the Duke of Beaufort; and correspondence concerning a stove ordered by Botetourt before his death and given to the Virginia House of Burgesses.
Series II: Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1787-1877, contains certificates, correspondence, mortgages, obituaries, portraits, powers of attorney, receipts, and treasury notes. Correspondence contains letter, 22 May 1815, from Alexander J. Dallas, Secretary of War, to Colonel Hugh Brady of Carlisle, Pennsylvania, concerning the military peace establishment of the United States; letter, 6 October 1851, from William A. Graham, Secretary of the Navy, to Dr. Robert A. Ashburn of Norfolk, Virginia, regarding the Navy examining board; letter, 7 May 1867, from Benson J. Lossing of Poukeepsie, New York, to J. C. Buttre concerning the signature of Abraham Lincoln; letter, n.d., from Anna Cora Mowatt (Mrs. William A. Ritchie), including a portrait and her obituary dated 17 August 1870; letters from William Eustis, Secretary of War, Albert Gallatin, Secretary of the Treasury, and John Smith, Chief Clerk for the Secretary of War, to Thomas Nelson, Commissioner of Loans for Virginia, Richmond, Virginia, regarding military pensions; letter, 26 October 1877, from Robert Toombs of Washington, Georgia, to J. Burton of New York, New York, acknowledging receipt of letter; and letter, 5 December 1827, from Samuel Southard, Secretary of the Navy, to President John Quincy Adams concerning the claim of Captain William H. Freeman of the Marine Corps.
Series II: also include certificates containing one from James Maury, United States Consul in Liverpool, England, for sale and transfer of the "Aurora," and one for membership to Dean S. Howard in the Washington Monument Society. Collection also contains a power of attorney, 13 June 1806, from Richard Dobson to Benjamin Day; receipt from Senator R. M. T. Hunter of Virginia to Asbury Dickins, Clerk of the Senate, for journals; mortgage, 9 March 1787, from Buckner and Ann Stith of Fairfax County, Virginia, to William Herbert of Alexandria, Virginia; and two treasury notes, 1838, from the government of Texas.
Organization
Collection is arranged into the following two series: Series I: Norborne Berkeley, Baron de Botetourt estate papers, 1770-1772; and Series II: Miscellaneous Manuscripts, 1787-1877. Series I is filed in Box 1 and Series II is filed in Box 2.
Contents List
- Letter, 15 August 1770, S. Buzaglu, London, [England], to [Norborne Berkeley, Lord Botetourt], [Williamsburg, Virginia], noting a shipment of stone and enclosing "Directions for using the Warming Machines.", 2 p., ALS., and 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder a-1)
- Letter, 30 October 1770, William Nelson, John Randolph, Robert Carter Nicholas, George Wythe, and John Blair, [Williamsburg], Virginia, to [Henry Somerset, Duke of Beaufort], informing him of the death of Lord Botetourt, Governor of Virginia, and his funeral. Also comments on the management of his estate and requests instructions. Includes an inventory of the Governor's Palace and outbuildings, catalogue of the library, and inventory of standing furniture., 27 p., ALS. (Folder a-2)
- Letter, n.d., [James] Horrocks, [London], to Robert Carter Nicholas [Williamsburg], directing Nicholas to pay the balance of Lord Botetourt's subscription for the workhouse to [John] Saunders., 1 leaf, ALS. (Box 1, Folder a-3)
- Letter, 2 January 1771, [Duke of] Beaufort, Badminton, [England], to William Nelson, et. al., [Williamsburg], stating he had received their letter of 30 October and sending thanks for services and funeral. Comments on monument for Botetourt, gives directions for settlement of estate, and requests account of the estate. Provides a list of things to be sent to England., 5 p., and 1 leaf, ALS. Typed copy of the list of things to be sent to England. (Box 1, Folder a-4)
- Letter, 28 January 1770 [1771], Thomas Conway, London, to Mr. [William] Marshman, Williamsburg, stating that the Virginia House of Burgesses is to have the stove., 2 p., ALS. (Box 1, Folder a-5)
- Letter, 27 May 1771, [Robert Carter Nicholas, et. al.], [Williamsburg], Virginia, to [the Duke of Beaufort], informing him that expenses have been paid and goods are packed, but no shpping is available. Also state that other property nearly sold. Credit has been extended and they accept the gift of portraits and carriage. Discuss monument to Botetourt, enclosing a memorandum on its location., 5 p., AL. (Box 1, Folder a-6)
- Letter, 8 June 1771, [Robert Carter Nicholas, et. al.], [Williamsburg], Virginia, to [the Duke of Beaufort] stating that passage for goods has been found on Captain John Cawsey's ship "Planter," owned by Farel and Jones of Bristol, [England]. Floods destroyed tobacco. Discuss the freight charges and insurance. State that William Marshman and Thomas Fuller, the managers of Botetourt's estate, will be leaving with Cawsey., 2 p., AL. (Box 1, Folder a-7)
- Letter, 25 July 1771, [Robert Carter Nicholas, et. al.], [Williamsburg], Virginia, to [the Duke of Beaufort], informing him that Captain Cawsey has been delayed, and that Marshman and Fuller will return to England with Captain Samson. Enclose shipping list, bill for boarding Marshman and Fuller, statement of cash received by Marshman for the estate, and a receipt for coal., 2 leaves and 9 p., AL. (Box 1, Folder a-8)
- Letter, 13 October 1771, [Duke of] Beaufort, Badminton, [England], to [William Nelson, et. al.], sending his thanks, and requesting copies of vouchers. He comments on statue of Lord Botetourt and states he received the draft., 2 p. Ms. (Box 1, Folder a-9)
- Letter, 6 March 1772, [Duke of] Beaufort, Grosvenor Square, [London, England], to [William Nelson, et. al.], [Williamsburg, Virginia] stating he has received their letters of 12 November 1771 and 2 January 1772. States that Captain Cawsey and his ship are probably lost. Comments on Mr. Norton and the statue., 2 p., ALS. (Box 1, Folder a-10)
- Bill of exchange, 28 November 1772, Richard Hanson to Robert Carter Nicholas on Lyonel and Samuel Lyde for 111 pounds, 17 shillings, and 11 pence sterling. Signed by Nicholas to the Duke of Beaufort., 2 p., printed form. (Box 1, Folder a-11)
- Letter, 22 May 1815, Alexander J. Dallas, War Department, to Colonel Hugh Brady, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, regarding the organization of the military peace establishment of the United States., 1 leaf, Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-1)
- Letter, 6 October 1851, William A. Graham, Secretary of the Navy, to Dr. Robert A. Ashburn, Norfolk, Virginia, concerning Ashburn's eligibility to appear before the Navy Examining Board., 1 leaf, Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-2)
- Power of attorney, 13 June 1806, from Richard Dobson to Benjamin Day. Attested by Stanton Slaughter, 17 June 1806, and certified by John Jameson, clerk of the Culpeper County, [Virginia], Court., 2 p., Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-3)
- Receipt, January 1855, Senator R. M. T. Hunter to Asbury Dickins, Secretary of the Senate, for Senate and House Journals and for the Reports of the Committees., 1 leaf, Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-4)
- Letter, 7 May 1867, Benson J. Lossing, Poughkeepsie, New York, to J. C. Buttre concerning Abraham Lincoln's signature., 1 leaf, ALS. (Box 2, Folder b-5)
- Certificate, 18 August 1809, of Sale and Transfer of the Aurora and its cargo from Thomas Dingley to Barnabas Otis. Certificate made by James Maury, United States Consul in Liverpool, England., 1 leaf, printed form. (Box 2, Folder b-6)
- Letter, n.d., from Anna Cora Mowatt [Ritchie] to an unidentified correspondent, and also containing a portrait of Anna Mowatt and her obituary, 17 August 1870, from a Boston, Massachusetts, newspaper., 3 leaves. (Box 2, Folder b-7)
- Letter, 8 April 1809, William Eustis, Secretary of War, to Thomas Nelson, Commissioner of Loans, Richmond, Virginia, appointing Nelson agent for payment of military pensions., 1 leaf, Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-8)
- Letter, 6 February 1810, Albert Gallatin, Secretary of the Treasury, to Thomas Nelson, Commissioner of Loans, Richmond, Virginia, regarding money for the payment of pensions. Gallatins states the need for a good accounting of the money., 2 p., Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-9)
- Letter, 27 July 1810, John Smith, Chief Clerk for the Secretary of War, War Deptartment, to Thomas Nelson, Commissioner of Loans, Richmond, Virginia, regarding payment of particular pensions., 1 leaf, Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-10)
- Mortgage, 9 March 1787, for 722 pounds, 17 shilliings, 6 pence on 301 1/2 acres and 18 slaves, from Buckner and Ann Stith, Fairfax County, Virginia, to William Herbert, Alexandria, Virginia. Proved 15 October 1787., 3 p., Ms. (Box 2, Folder b-11)
- Treasury notes, 1838, issued by the government of Texas. First note: $3 denomination 10% interest, 1 June 1838. Second note: $20 denomination 10% interest, 1 September 1838., 1 leaf, photocopies. (Box 2, Folder b-12)
- Letter, 26 October 1877, Robert Toombs, Washington, Georgia, to J. Burton, New York, New York, stating that he received Burton's letter., 1 leaf, ALS. (Box 2, Folder b-13)
- Membership certificate, 10 July 1851, from the Washington National Monument Society to Dean S. Howard., 1 leaf, printed form. (Box 2, Folder b-14)
- Letter, 5 December 1827, Samuel Southard, Secretary of the Navy, to President John Quincy Adams, concerning the case of Captain William H. Freeman of the United States Marines., 1 leaf, ALS. (Box 2, Folder b-15)